you
hi all good evening
so how's everyone
I'll share my screen hope I'm audible guys I'm audible and visible you can see my screen share
I'll have some timer before we get started with class let's put it 3 minutes
we'll start exactly at 9.05
I did
so any doubts from the previous sessions or like how's your assignment going
any doubts guys from previous session hope everyone have solved their assignments who are present in the class currently
I see lower in number but
very good great munish
so usually we get a people get drop on Saturday right
what to choose for submit
will exactly implement from both but it's like a you know input type or submit button right
so even if you are getting a button is an you know HTML5 semantic
like semantic element where you when you select the input type
input and give type equal to you know submit then it will be used in the same way
so it is your choice like whether you can use it anything
okay
so
I see less people joining class today can anyone help me or dropping a message in WhatsApp group
like we are able to get started please join us
can anyone help me out or should I drop it
let me do this give me a second guys
hey thank you munish
inform of what purpose using method, post or get
Kabir will see that in future classes okay
about method, post and get actually when we will build APIs and we will deal with it
I am supposed to explain completely in depth
we will take it at that time okay
currently the agenda is was earlier to understand elements and HTML part
today we will understand interaction part of CSS then we will go ahead
it's not mandatory submit it depends on the use cases that you are using
three of the attributes okay
attributes are generally enhancing the existing elements
so whatever attributes you needed you can add as per your specific
but there is nothing as such mandatory
action also yes
everything related to action because it's a redirection right
URL being changed give me a second guys I will connect iPad
and we will get started with today's class
okay
so I hope everyone is able to see the iPad screen
yeah
two people are there
we usually have problem with Abhishek's in class
there are too many Abhishek's in class
in India we have too some bits
great guys
so let's get started
we have good enough amount of people today
to get started with
so the class three today is an introduction to CSS class
okay
and we are able to get started with CSS
but what all things we will be discussing is
what is CSS
and when to use it
we already knew it but it's just a revision
then we will go with selectors
then once selectors is done we will talk about fonts
then we will check
we will work on colors
we will discuss some things on colors
then if time permits
we will go with the background
okay
so
CSS is a topic
which people all like you know
it's a one of the topic
where people try to avoid it
or don't think of much
because it's sometimes people feel it's difficult
but I will try to make sure that
it's as easy as possible
and as comfortable as possible
okay guys
so now
getting started with today's topic
first topic
so introduction to CSS
I think we have already discussed
when to use CSS
if anyone remembers the example
that we discussed
about house
building
and what was the part that
you have paint right
anyone else like interiors, paint
right
cool
so this is the part
if you remember the example of house
we were considering this part
so this is same thing
now we will talk about
let's say we have built HTML content
we are at the point
now we have to decide how to paint it
or what wall to choose
how to choose a wall
okay as I have told you earlier
in HTML
you have only two things
what are the two things that I have told you
anyone remember those two things
like only two things
are there in the HTML
that you need to remember
all the things you can
no worries
I have told you there are only two things
which are elements
or tags
and then you have something called attributes
I mean everything comes under these two sections
there are elements
or tags
and each element tag is enriched
or adding more functionality
we add it using attributes
as such when it comes to CSS
there are three things
so what are the three basic things
that you have to deal with it when it comes to CSS
let's say
first thing
is like what
then where
and how
let's take an example of
like you went to a barber shop
right
I am considering a mail
option guys
pardon me if I am not taking a gender neutral one
but let's say you went for a
barber shop
where you want to cut your hair
so let's say
I am saying that
I want to cut my hair
no
so now
when you enter the barber shop
you would explain barber
which hair you want to cut it
either hair or the beard
so you have to define it
do you agree with me
you have to tell him explain him
isn't it
so if I say
it's like head hair
now once it is done
do you guys agree
like you have to explain him how
like what style you need it
or else what if you make a Mahatma Gandhi style
like hair style
so you would be amazed right
after half an hour or one hour
after your haircut is done
so you have to explain him
the kind of style
like when it goes to style
you know
Koli style
which get trimmed on the side and somewhat
in old days
and few years back
Dhoni's long hairs were famous
so even few people
remove their hair completely
you can say
you can say Gandhiji
because I never seen a picture with
Gandhiji where having
too much of hair
and then
or the you know many styles
but are you getting my point
that whenever you are going
or like
wherever you want to beautify your hair
like when you go to barber
you will tell what
cut the hair and which hair
like where head hair
then you have to tell him the style
same thing happens in the
when it comes to CSS
now
cutting the hair
so when I am cutting the hair
I mean to say that what all properties
that I am going to deal with
like using a color or height
or let's say
width
or font
right so these are the different
types that you want to do it
and for which item you want to do it
this could be the all
HTML elements
okay
and how would you do it
is that you will define
for color could be red
right height could be 200px
and width could be 150px
right
and font could be again
12px
so these are the way how you can do it
but what is the exact syntax
like how you define a list of CSS
like first clause
goes to the where
now what do I mean by where
is like you have to select which HTML
you want to apply multiple things
once you open the brace
then you can define
each property of hair
or like I mean what and then
like how let's say you want to
make it a color
let's say what
and how so this is how the
combination goes like
is this
clear guys
like how does it work
basically you have to remember
these things like first you have to select
an HTML element
and then you have a list
of properties in terms of key value pair
each property will go for
what type of changes you want to do
in style like what is
the category comes in then
what is the exact value for that one
these are the list of things
let's see
this one
let's see this one firstly while taking one example
let me share
the code base
so if you see
I have created a new folder called
CSS class 3
and I will build one of the file called
let's say index.html
now
I say HTML.5
let's just take one example
guys
showing it how you can do it
now if you want to
style it right
as I have told you
one of the way is to you know
you write it down in the head
let me open
this is coming
fine
now let's say I open a style block here
inside the head
and I say def
and I say color
to be red
so what did I do here
I have added a one def tag
then
I have told like hey I am selecting
this particular
this thing like an element HTML element
once I selected HTML element
I have chosen it like what I want to deal
with this one
once I selected where and then
this is the what condition this is how
right
I hope this basic thing is clear for you
is any doubt
still no like
yeah
first thing
what you have to do is like if you want to
style any particular thing
you have to select an HTML element
now we will see there are too many
ways of selecting an HTML element
what I have did is here I have used an element
selector I have selected this particular
def and I set it like this def
I mean to say that
where I have to do it like I am selecting
this image this means that I have to
paint something or do something to this particular
element once I have
done that then I can customize
it using different properties that
I want to do ok
let's say I say that font size
let's say
larger when I do this
so you can see the size is increasing or else
you can use the pixels which are 50px
ok
what if there are two diffs something will
come to that I will come to the many selectors
ok but this is just
one file where I am explaining this
ok like how do
you do it just introduction to
CSS now
there are too many things
like 3 particular
ways of selecting like how you can do
you know add styles
ways of adding
CSS
let's say I
create a file inside
this again index.html
let's rename
this one
once you have this
no
let's close this
let's open this one
open show preview
let's say ways of
adding CSS
ok generally
you can add CSS like
to one particular HTML document
in three ways ok we will discuss
about the first thing first way
let's say I have a paragraph
and I have let's say lorem20
and I generated a
paragraph of 20 size and if I
want to apply a style
I can do it this way
where I can say color blue
or blue violet let's say this one
ok this type of
style whenever you are doing it inside
element itself here
you need not to select element because
the element is already selected
we are writing it directly there what type of properties
you want to add that
whenever you are doing this type of
styling it is generally called as
inline style
is this point clear guys what is
inline style and one way of writing
styles to an HTML element
now then there is a
second way what you can do is that
let's say you have another p tag
let's say s lorem
ok now
let's say I have a style
inside this if I do p and
this way and I say color
and I say brown
now if you see
this is
now what I did is like I went
I created a style block inside
the head tag that's where you have to
create a style block inside
this style element I have added
one p like I have selected p selector
I mean generally
it is called as element selector we will come back to
those each type of selectors
but I selected p and then I have added
a color called as brown
ok so
this type of whenever you
write down this like inside a style block right
then it is generally called as
internal css
ok guys
what is internal css what is inline
css whenever you add
onto that element directly
that is called as inline css
whenever you add inside a style block
but in the same file
ok you are defining all the styles then it is called
as internal css
is this clear guys
no reactions
why don't we mention
which p need to be selected in red
how it is represented
so I shall come to that now
if you see it here one question I would
generally you know
one should come to your mind
is like hey I have defined
p colored brown
now both tags are
p but this color
is still blue violet
and this color is still
in brown color
right like both
should be brown or like one
like both should be brown right that's what
we are expecting or like which is getting
priority or how it is getting handled
so remember one thing
whenever you have multiple
types of css are defined right
most you know css
is executed or any html file
is executed from top to bottom
now whenever you are executing from top to bottom
let's say your style block is defined
here head will be passed
anyways first now once it is being
passed you have told that hey p selected
to be brown now once you
selected p equal to brown but
when you come down and you are passing this one
you have defined again style
color to be blue violet
that overridden it now let's say if
I you are overriding
color but what if you have a font size
and let's say I have till 15
pixel now if you see
the font size is affecting both the things
font size is affecting both the things now but
again if I override it here let's say
I override here saying font size
20 pixel
you see this
it is so what I mean
to explain here is that
css or html is being passed
from top to bottom now whatever
you have defined here doesn't
matter if you are writing inline
style that will get a priority
yeah you can say weightage of inline
overrides always but
you have to understand
this so that how it is actually why is happening
behind the scenes when you are coming from top
to bottom it is executed top to bottom
and this is the last line
to get executed and when you are defining
here directly it is supposed to
attach those styles
is that clear guys?
okay
I hope like inline and internal
are clear now
then there is another way where you can have
your own style sheets like
let's say I say that style.
css file I have created a
news file now
I have to link this file now
these two files are you know separate
but I have to tell that hey I want to link
this particular
let's
focus on this guys then I will take the questions
okay now
let's say I have the style
file separately now
I have to link those particular
style.css file with this index.html
file anyone knows like how we can
do that
no so let's
say you have one tag
again here link tag
okay
not in the style but I have to write
above style let's say
link
okay once you have link
tag right
okay inside link
tag you can always you know
you can give href whenever we are saying
href we mean to say that
location of the file
location of the url so I am saying
that I have to go into the same folder
and then select the style.css file
once I select that then
I have to write the other attribute
is like type or
like relation now
what is the relation to this
how that css file is related to
this html file
we say that as a style sheet
now
let's say once now we
have defined let's say I have another
p tag where
I have let's say
I have a bigger paragraph
now the brown color is
being applied now let's say if I
go in here and I
say that color should
be tomato
what would be
your guess guys
I didn't save it yet but
do you think tomato color should be applied
to any of these paragraphs
right one says yes
two people says yes
why do you think charm
or hariprasad
it will be all
on all three ok dhanraj says all three
ok let's see
now I will save this
if you see I applied tomato
do you see anywhere that tomato is
being applied
no right now let's do one thing
what if I comment this line
let's say what if I comment this line
let's say comment this line
do you see that now tomato is being applied
so what's happening as I just told you right now
that you know all the things
that whatever you write it
is being passed from top to bottom
I have defined a link stylesheet here
so it will download it here
then it will see that hey
paragraph tag color says you know
p tag color says tomato
then fine again a style tag is
defined here p tag says that brown in
color so the tomato is left
behind because new
color has been given now
when you go to the here now the color
is overwritten but till for this
two paragraph tags the color is not yet
overwritten
is this clear why tomato
is not coming guys
this is happening in the
hierarchy from top to bottom
now let's say what if I pull this link
and I put it
here down
what do you think
it applied that style
now is this point
clear when I pull it up from top
and putting bottom now the orange is
being applied is this reasoning
clear enough to you all guys
right so CSS generally
passed from top to bottom
now and by and
the second point that we learned is like
what are the different types of adding
CSS like this is called
something called as external CSS
okay so generally
you have three types of ways of writing
a CSS one is internal one is
external and one is
inline CSS
okay so
always you can believe that preference
will be inline
but whenever you have definition
I don't want to say that
hey remember two things just remember this way
that execution happens from top to
bottom and whenever
however you have defined whatever comes
at the last that will be attached because
that is overriding that particular property
to this particular HTML element
is this clear guys like
how we are able to apply
we are selecting a particular element
we are grouping multiple properties
to it and attaching it
so I hope this three things
how we are making it
like you know work you got it
but let's say
okay this is fine now we will go
to types of selectors
if you see here
what did I do is like each and every time
like
what I did is like I have always selected
p tag right always selected
p tag and I have applied
it this way do you think that this
would be suffice in the
world like real time world like only
selecting directly HTML elements
and applying CSS you would be able
to handle all the complexities
that exist in the world this is
isn't it and this is not enough right
or like you have you can have multiple
divs inside div
and you can have ten layers of div
acting as a section right
so for dealing with all those cases
right different cases
we have many different types of
you know the selectors
we will discuss one by one
like selectors using
I have built one of the you know
best way to teachers like
using a question and answer type
format so let's say
we will take questions
like format like one by one questions and then we will
understand okay let's say
I create a folder called selectors
and I create one I say
q1 question one dot html
okay we have this
question one dot html
let me copy the question guys
so
show
so if you see this one guys
like
what's being done here
so there are multiple h1
tags which says I am paragraph
help me to become h1
okay h1 dot
now what the
question is add CSS
styles to the all h1 tags making
it blue okay
any suggestions guys how we can
do this
make all the
h1 tags
like blue in color
we have just seen now I hope
like everyone can write down
inline style
I think I have received
good enough answers
so few questions also
so what while teaching
it right while teaching it I will use
this you know internal CSS
to write it down since it would be
difficult for me to switch the files I will write down
all in the style block itself okay
so here so first thing I have
since if you see the question I
have to make all the h1s
to the blue so I have to
select only first like h1 tag
so when I am selecting h1
then I am opening the brace now I have to say
that color equal to blue
as many of I have already
suggested okay now
what type of selector is
this what type of
selector is this
anyone any idea what type
of selector what we call this type of
selectors or
what is a h1
no
no I am not talking about internal
CSS or external CSS
I agree with you this is an
internal CSS but when I am
going to select h1
yeah some
people think tag selector
something element selector so guys
we call this as element selector
okay
so whenever
you are directly selecting this
whenever you are selecting directly
like using this HTML
elements like whatever you are
picking that item and applying styles
to it directly that is what we
call as element selector is this clear
element selector you will remember right
everyone
so we will move to the question
two ways let's say
let me pick the question two
yeah
q2.html
let me copy this
so I will give you some chance
you know to read this question first
then I will open the preview
so that you know everyone can see it
so what this
you know question is talking about
select the obvious p tags
and make class one
as blue
and class two as red
okay
class is used to share common list of
cells for different elements that's okay
that's a quote that I might have written
earlier but
what we are trying to say is that
hey you have now
all the p tags right
do you guys agree you have all the p tags
now as
we have solved this last problem
if we go and select
the p tag and make it color blue
or you know red
this question might not be
wouldn't be solved right because it would be affecting
these randoms also
right
so we have to
individually select
individually select them
and make it red and blue
okay now when we want to
solve this particular type of things
right
we tend to use all
attributes that are available
okay now what was
the attribute available for us
which type of attribute is
available for us to deal with this
class right
so now
if you want to add a style
to any class right
now if you see I have a class one and
class two as an E
firstly I have to select let's say
class one element what I will do is that
I use a dot operator
I say that hey
class one so whenever
we are using we are defining
a CSS for a class type of
attribute we use a dot operator
okay remember that thing
now it is asking me
make me blue so I will select
that color and blue
okay now if you see
only class one got
this particular thing got affected nothing else
got affected similarly I will
go and do this class two
and I will make it red
is this clear guys
how class can be utilized
and how element selector can be
utilized if you let's say
if I want to attach a common
like you know let's say I want to make all
the tags
that are present
like fonts as equal to 16
how can how can I make
it
how can I make it if I want to make all
the fonts that are present here in the page
equal to 16 pixels
I will come to pixel
whatever whenever I am using
PX I will come to that
but now Upendra and
Chandni are suggesting let's go select
the P tag and make font size
equal to 16 pixels
because we want to apply
for the everything
when we are applying for everything by
default we can select all the P tags
right
is this clear guys
apply to body
so one says apply to the body
but what would be the right way
of doing it was to apply
to the P tag directly right
you can apply to the body also but
I don't want to do that let's say
18 pixels
so I hope when to use element
selector when to use class selector is
clear now going with the
next question
give me a second guys I will pick it up
okay
I have
Q3
question 3.
HTML
again closing this
let's keep this open
okay
so now earlier
someone had asked me question like
whether a style block should be
only present inside head tag
right or what if I can
add somewhere else you can surely
add anywhere else but I would suggest
you know to add it inside the head
tag that's I'm just showing for you
guys like you can add it bottom also
okay but
you should follow best practices
go and add it in the head tag actually
generally you don't write
mostly you know
internal CSS or inline CSS
as you go for the frameworks
always will be something will be preferred
as external CSS okay
now so coming back to the question
guys here
if you see here
what's happening here
so they are saying that select
S2 with the ID
the one and make it blue
so they are saying what they are saying is that
only this thing okay
what is our like select me
they are asking us to select only
that particular HTML element
and make it blue
any ideas like if you know the
answer you know write it down to me
personally like don't write
it down in the comment chat
but any guesses guys do you think here
I can apply element selector
or the class selector
if I apply element
selector it will apply all the random
and select me if I apply
class selector then
if you see here all
this randoms also will be selected right
because this is also S2 class
right so when
you have this thing right now
what whenever you have this type of problem
right all the attacks are same type of elements
all the classes are also having
like common classes
then you should go and see that hey
which attribute I can use
do you see there is a one unique attribute
for select me
ID right as Muneshwara
suggested
so what we will do is like
we will go and select ID
now if you want to select an ID
type of attribute right you have
to use hash key
and you should write the one
ok
let's say I have to
make it blue so I will
make it as blue
and we will open this in preview
ok now
do you guys understand this how to add
ID whenever you
use ID selector you have to use
hash key ok
currently the things we have discussed
this we write element
selector ID selector and class
selector these are really common and you will
be using it across now
so whoever asked me like whether I can use
style block below let's say I go
and put it below the body
still it works because it's still
passing the one means
like if you see the ID
whichever the ID is
the value
of it
ok now but following
the standard guys I will go
and put it in the head itself style is supposed
to be there ok
yeah ok
to clear the supendra's doubt
so let's say I have style
here guys now
let's say this is an
internal CSS right what
if I go and write down
style here and I make
color equal to blue
or color equal to red
which color should
apply blue or red
ok how many people are suggesting red
give me thumbs up for the red and thumbs
down for the blue
so all the people are going with
red ok let's say I will make it
red
ok spelling mistake
ok
no so what happened here
ok so for this thing
how this is getting executed
is like
so whose question was this
I just want to open
now why this happened right
though we told that
hey from top to bottom
whatever style should define
it should override it now the
style block is defined at the bottom
and the blue is not overriding it
that would be basic question right
that's a confusing statement again
but behind the scenes what's happening is
like when your DOM is created
I will come back to it but like when we talk
about DOM like how DOM tree is
created from that perspective
this things right
this style block
it last right whenever you are creating
this type of structure let's say
I will go and
show it to you guys
ok
now if you see
how tree you know DOM
tree is formed is first we know that
there is an HTML element it has
two things head and body
ok
then head
might have some meta attacks
right style links
then this have
multiple piece
right
now similarly
when you are building a DOM
DOM is generally
built for you know this one
what we say
HTML element but there is something called
Syscom
ok
Syscom is applied to
you know define which CSS should apply
now this tree
generally when it is applying right
firstly it will go through
like external
any if there are any
internal right it will try to read it
now there is a
clarity firstly who is winning
between them is decided
now after that whenever you are
building a tree right let's say whenever
you are applying let's say body
is there here now
all the
P tags are here let's say
in external
file you have defined color as
red and in internal you
made it blue considering
link is added
above style
in internal
ok so first
it is red then overridden with blue
now let's say for this one you have
added inline
ok now firstly
all these things are resolved but when
you are building a tree right actually
it will say that hey I am building a
P tag I will check what are the colors
anything is there that I have to apply
it says that blue ok
applied here also blue applied
here also blue here let's say
for inline you made it here
again red let's say so red will be
updated so this is how it happens
like structure it like
inline will be preferred at max
like there is also
one of the other rules that we will see
like what like there is one
something that specificity
we will see in the future classes
when it comes to it what are the rules
like which style will be applied
ok for that reason
what I usually say right
you know if you don't want to confuse
yourself right always
add the style block on to the top
of it don't focus
don't confuse yourself keep it clarity
because you are the developer there wouldn't
be anyone asking you to add
style below or why didn't you add up
so following coding standards there
will be a clarity to you it's not like
multiple ways of doing it
what is the right way of doing it
is that fine guys
I will explain again how html
and syscom like
dom and syscom is there then
how a
aom is built actually
which is like exactly a copy of a browser
web screenshot of website
we will see in the future classes
I will pick it up I will also share you a document
which you can refer to and understand
how actually all these things like
once we understand javascript
html and sys how these three
are combined and how they work all together
okay now
going back to next
question guys
q4
dot html
let's say this one
now if you see this
question here
yeah inline will override always something
but understand behind
the reasons why it would be that no one
like rules happen built
simply generically
you should understand how behind the scenes
are happening we will see that in the
future classes okay
now but coming back to this
question guys if you see here there's a
form element it says you know
input button type button
it says click me and select me
now
so what it is saying
and select the input element with the
value select me and make it
make its background color blue
okay
so do you see anything that you can
apply by the knowledge you have till now
do you think that
element selector would work
or you know any selector
that's there here do you see any
class or id
no right even the type is like
buttons are same
so always always
look at it this way like always look at
it this way whenever you are not sure
of doing anything look at like
attributes do you
say one attribute is differing here
value right
yeah so they just suggest
that attribute selector now we'll see what
is like attribute selector is like how do
you handle that attributes because
each type of selector whenever you are writing
there's a different definition of
writing it right like how you define them
now let's say this is an attribute
selector
okay
now how do you use it attribute selector
now what type of
element is this guys that we want to
select
what type of element is this
HTML element
input right first you
write down input then you
write down like value
okay
so first select the HTML element
in bracket you define the
attribute that you want to select
select me
once you do this
then open the brace and let's say
background color
to the blue
now let's open the
preview
do you see this
background color blue is added
so this is how you write
down attribute selector like any
attribute other than class
id or you know element
if you have let's say
generically you can add any number of attributes
let's say even if you say
let's say data
test id this
doesn't exist though I'm making
it let's say I say this
is a one
and let's say I go in here
add input
data
test id
let's say I select
this
and I say
this is a one
background
color
to be
brown
if you see this you can add anything
let's say in randomly you have
something like let's say you want to select it uniquely
but you don't have anything common
so you can select any
attribute that you have and attributes
can be anything any number of attributes you can
define for one html element
there are few defined by html
few you can define anything now I use
like this some random is this clear guys
attribute selector clear
so I hope all the four type
of selectors are clear till now element
id class and
attribute selector and now next
will go to some you know
bit of
combinatorics like this are simple one
let's say I go for
q5
dot html
let's say
I copy this
and
let's
close this
let's open now
if you see here what this is talking
about so it is talking about
write css selector to select the obvious
list of items to make it blue
so
what it is saying that select
me whatever select means there right li
tags li tags inside
this diff ol and li
so it is asking us to
select them and make it blue
now till now I told that
hey if you have an element
do it if you have an attribute
pick that one but here we don't have
ability
to pick it element selector because
if I pick li tag directly
this will be also converted
into blue right and we don't have
any attributes also to make it
blue so
do you see any possibility that
we can use our current knowledge
in selectors and solve this question
use diff
so okay
I make a diff
and let's say I will also
have a diff here
to make it further difficult
I will have a diff here
let's say okay
diff also works fine let's say
I have a diff then also it will solve that
so how many of you guys agree that
selection of diff will solve the problem
okay now
let's say
I go to style block
I open diff
and let's say color
equal to blue
okay
so it is making all blue
but is there any
other way that you want to do let's say
you also have
ol tag
there is an extra ol tag here
let's say this is something present
now so
as I made this complicated
now think of this way
like if I have
let's say this is a ul tag here
specifically
okay
on order at least
think of it like if you want to select only
select me here
now I am having
both the things have made it
to blue
I have to make it only one
like select me only
so Teja says
diff ol
okay
so
guys I want to introduce here
a new type of selector what we call it
like this is
a combination
okay
you have to use combinations
of
different selectors from
now on
since only one
like directly if I select
diff I am not able to solve
because earlier using diff
you were able to solve but I made
complicated now like using a diff
you might not be able to select this one
right using
li you won't be able to select it
now whenever you are not able to select it
and attributes are not helpful
you should go for the combinations you have to search
firstly directly element
then attributes if attributes are
not supportive then go for combination
okay now writing
a combination there is one type
of combination that you can use is
called as descendant selector
okay descendant
selector now let's see google
descendant
this
I have to
okay
so what it is telling guys
if you can see this
can anyone I hope you are reading
this one originating or coming
from a ancestor stalker source
right whenever you say that
have anyone have seen
any code notices or anything
like they write you know descendants of
this person
like whenever you have something ancestor
property coming to your name
so you are considered your descendants of
your four grandfathers
right
so whenever you are saying
that descendant selector you mean to say
that like defining
what is parent and direct child
like let's say now what do I exactly mean by
is that that now if you see
I have div tag
I will select for surely because this is something
like a grandfather let's say I have
selected div now
after that what I can
do is like I can directly say
li tag
div
li color
blue
okay now if you see
when I am selecting li
I am making it blue both but
if I want to make it you know different
I have to select ol
okay as already
Teja has suggested
but how do we define
this this is like a descendant
now whenever you select one parent
let's say I can always
I can also do this
using let's say
you can like you can use it
anyways like from body also you can start
it like descendant goes from
top parent like this is a
parent element and these are the children
element okay similarly
this is the grandfather you can say
parent and then child so multi
levels so what we are doing
is like from descendant so you are getting from
ancestral you know tag
html element you are talking about
like what is a wrapper first wrapper
you are starting from there then you are
selecting here div inside div select
the ol
is this clear guys descendant selector
how this works so
here we have combined
what if we have to color only
select okay what if we have to color
only select right now
I will show you this
but some bit I will come
back to this one let's say there is an nth
child I will select one
give me a second then I have to
go to li
okay if you
see this what did I make I have
chosen grand parent
parent child
inside that if I have multiple
childs I have selected
first child out of it
this is okay some bit I will remove it as
of now I have just answered your question
just let's focus
on descendant selector okay
because this notes will be referred again
for your sake
so I hope this question is cleared
but coming back to
next question guys
now let's say there is another
type of combination you can
use
let's say I use q6
dot html
okay I am again closing this
please read through so what I am saying
is that select I am
direction and make it blue
guys we have just now
learned descendant selector
think of it we have learned
actually too many selectors now
think of it like if you can apply any one
of them
if you can apply any one of them like
you have element selector
you have id selector
you have attribute selector
you have class selector
we started with
combinations we went and
thought of like descendant selector
if you go from descendant
you start from top level
even you go from body
or you go from div
think of it like
someone says div h1
span
okay
let's see this
what I will do is
div h1
span
color blue
now I will open
show preview
so here there is something happening guys
do you think our question is solved
no right
so combinations
can be used here but
there is a different type of combinations
here we have to use
we can add a class
and we can solve some with anyways
right but here we have to use
a combination so
one of the other type of combination
that we can discuss is something called
as children selector
okay
so children is something we say
that who is next
to our life like let's say if I
if I have a future my
babies I will say that they are my children
right but my grandfather cannot say
that they are my children he will say that they are my
granddaughters and grandsons right
do you
agree with this frame first like
in future if you have babies
they will say that they are your children but grandfather
will say that grandchildren so whenever
we are saying that children selector right
you have to be specific
so whenever we are going through that
hierarchy series so when
we see that this is our dev tag
then h1 tag and span
so div will say hey
if you see here inside div
if I want to select this specifically
this one right inside this
this child is h1 so I will say that hey
for selecting child I will use this
greater than symbol
whenever I use greater than symbol I mean
to say that hey dev child
h1 h1 child
span
do you see this
how it is working
so when I am saying that whenever you are using
children selector you have
to define a complete relationship
till that element
till the element you reach it
like you have to reach you want to reach this element
what if you want to reach
this element what if you want to reach
this element like you can say
dev
span
and let's say color red
okay
so I am saying that whatever inside
this wrapper anything is there
make it red or else if you want to
specifically go and touch this span
right you have to keep on writing
the children selector h1
then again span
is this clear
like how you can use
children selector how you can write down
this series so children
goes for like each level
like if I write
down like statement I have
written one statement if you want to remember
this try to remember it this way
you have to reach
that particular html
if you want to remember this way
don't stop it in mid layer you can
always do div greater than h1
and that will apply color blue
but you know one thing
I would want to say that whenever using
combinations right even when you are in projects
go till that target element
and only then
apply the css
so that it doesn't affect in the future
okay so I hope
guys all the six questions are clear
to you like the different types of selectors
we introduced till now
I think I have one more
I question I guess
let me search for it
let's say I have
one interesting question
this is just a confusion
confusing question just want to
see like
how we can solve this
okay
now if you see it here
so what it is talking about is select the element
with the multiple classes m1 and m2
make them blue
okay they are talking about
like select me
like they are asking us to make this blue
not me or not me
this one m1 m2
if I
do m1
and make it blue
this will make both this blue
okay if I make m2
and make it blue this will make both
blue
okay this is also one of the
combination type of combination
only but this is on a class
you know class
selector
firstly we know right how we can write a class
okay
I have received one answer
but
right we remember class selector right
what if I can if I want to
go to specific item right if I want to
point at one specific item
can I consider
this class name as m1 m2
itself
you know those both class
are there I just go have to
get that name right specific element
I am targeting so I will do that
same thing whenever there is a class selector I will say that
dot m1
and dot m2
and let's say
color blue
let's see if this is applying
okay it didn't happen
give me a second
yeah so there shouldn't be space
whenever you are writing continuous elements
okay only for descendant happen
since this is a name right
we are using add a name and
classes generally use you
use dot operator okay
I hope this is clear guys
how can you access this multiple classes
just go by name
okay
so
is this clear guys like
I hope everyone
is having a good understanding on this
okay nice
isn't it m1 and m2
a single class
yeah somewhere that is what I was talking about
m1 and m2
consider this as a
single class and
this one as a different classes
so
m1 m2
okay let's say this
way it wouldn't work whenever
whatever you are defining inside
a class right you use
you need to use a dot operator
even let's say I have
id here
let's say this is
m1 id cannot be
having a multiple things firstly id should be unique
classes can be common
that's how it works
okay why dot in between
then hey guys
this is one class name
this is another class name I am using this
combination
I am specifically
pointing this on these are two whenever
you want to apply multiple classes let's say
this is m3 and you have
m4 multiple classes if you have
let's say one m3 class
dot m3 class is having some other properties
also font size
right let's say 20 pixel
so you want to apply
them right you cannot
yeah so
you have to use dots for each type of
class name because there is a space
space is given only when you have to add multiple
classes to one particular html
element you can have
n number of classes attached
to one class okay it's a
like it takes multiple things
okay so
nice so going back
removing this too
okay then there is another question
guys let's say
I think I have
solve this solve this
this is something
again a combination
think of this like how would you solve this
q8
q8.html
typo mistake okay
did I make anything here
okay
fine close this
now coming
back to this one I'm
pasting this question guys please go through it
so here
what it is saying is to select
direct sun and make it blue
so the
direct sun right and the direct sun is present
inside the dev track
first children which is p
here it is present here this way
now think of it how would you
deal with this one
there are many ways of writing this one
so think of this one
you can apply
to c2
one way I agree
open draw
one way is directly selecting
c2 and the
other suggestion Ashish has
given
you are targeting wrong element
I believe right if you see dev span and
p it says that I am in direction
but we want to target
under direction
now okay
shambhure says
dev children selector p
right okay cool
okay
now so there are many ways
of doing it so I'll write down all possible
things one was .c2
okay and making it color
blue okay
so this is like when you have enough knowledge
right you will be able to see there are many things
that you can do one is c2 directly
then the other suggestion that I got
was use children selector
dev and then p
then go for color blue
right this is also one
way now the third way
that I was thinking about is like
combination of let's say I use
.c1
and
let's say combination of this one
p
right what I did
what I did is like I have combined two
elements like using children selector
the c1 class and p
right so
three ways of solving this problem
is this clear guys like
you can directly select that element
or you can go from parent to child using
element selector what did I
combine here I have combined
element selector and class selector
and I have used a combinator
using children selectors
okay now
good good guys
I think you are able to understand this one
better now
one thing I have
is I think I have completed exhausted all
the things that I want to cover
give me a second
eight okay one question
I have guys I will give it as a homework
you have selected
like let's say q9
q9.html
okay
I will give it as homework I don't need
anyone answering it so that
you can answer it whenever
you have time
or I will ask in the
next class like I will push this anyways in
the get up okay think of
this one okay if you
see here what was this
select the element with select me and make it
simple so these are the
two things p tag and
div tag okay
I have wantedly made
some cumbersome this one
there are c1 c2
applying it multiple places so you
cannot use
actually I shouldn't talk about
you will get any all the hints that
you can think of you can eliminate the processes
and you can think of it I will push
this code okay now
coming back to
one of the things guys
you know these are the list of selectors that we
have seen but if you
remember one person someone
have questioned me
in one question like I have written
somewhere nth child right nth child
which question I have written I
don't remember okay
yeah please try it some bit I will also
what we will say what we will do is we will start a doubt
session after this sorry
doubt session I meant to say break I will
keep that open tab okay you can
think of it okay
but I was wanted to use something
okay no
where is button
give me a second guys I am trying
to find okay coming back to this question
let's open this in the
preview now
guys have you observed many times that
you know yeah I will push the code
but have you observed this thing many times that
whenever you go and write
hover over something
the button comes up or there's some
style changes are happening
or images coming up right whenever you
go move your cursor on it
right like
all those things are happening do you
do you know how we haven't seen
that thing right how we handle such behaviors
now that
that sort of things are called as pseudo
selectors okay now
we have covered simple selectors but
that comes under the pseudo selector I will
I will show you one of the examples how we
can do it just let's say I
want to make this button
background color change
yeah so let's say input
data test ID
to insert I will make it one
again okay
now
what I can do
is like all the behaviors right there are
too many behaviors to be specific
you can explore it
what you can do is like if you want to add any
pseudo selectors you can use double
dots once you have double dots
you can go below right
you will have something called hover
okay if you
see this hover so what it
means is that whenever you hover over
this button or like select me button
I will change something let's
say what I will make is like you know
add a border
I will come to the border properties guys everything
we will discuss is discuss this
but let's say I make one pixel
solid tomato
okay
what do I mean is that now if you see
this here the behavior if I
go and hover over click me nothing is
much happening because this is by default
we are getting this what
is of data test ID I have made
it just a random attribute to show
that you can add multiple attributes
into any
HTML random
okay so
now let's see if I go over select
hover me right if you see this
there is something orange is added
let me make 10 pixel
to show it if you see
this orange is coming up by
whenever I hover over it
so this side of this
things right you have to explore
further like what are properties can be
as of now this class
covers like how can you
select one particular element in multiple
ways and how can you reach that
so that you can add multiple behaviors
to it okay
we will see in future classes how we can deal
with hover or other things upcoming
clear guys
and also what I did
is like
what did I do it is that
if you go in the links right
show preview
right so I have added here
CSS selectors this link I will
push the code you can refer to this
you know and you can explore
all the things because this will need
reading time I try to make
a questionnaire such that you know we can cover
all the type of questions and understand and
one can go through it anytime
but if you want to read a documentation
docs by specific you can use
CSS selector hyperlink you can
go to it okay
now coming back to this one
I just want to summarize what we
have discussed in terms of selectors
right we have
we have discussed different types
of selectors can anyone help
me out naming what type of
things we have covered till now
right anyone
we covered something called
element
class
ID
attribute
then we went for
descended
then we went for children
right these are the
things that we have used right
when you go for class
you have to use dot operator and
class name you go for ID you have
to use hash key and when you go for
attribute you have to give element
name
and in array bracket
you have to define attribute value
go for descend descendant
any level you
can define the parent like dev
and li it will work
for descendant when it comes to
children you have to define the exact
hierarchy of elements reaching
the target value when you go for
element you can directly select any
element that you have and make
you know add styles to it
okay I hope this this all selectors
are clear to you so if this
thing is clear we'll
go for the five minutes break guys
I'll see there's a one question for
me that was
we want to add a transition speed and
all and hover should we add
some ways I'll cover that in doubt session
that's a big thing like I'll
since it's an introduction I will discuss
that okay
cool so
do you want me to take a break
or do you want me to continue guys
you need a break or you want me to please
push the code before break so we need
sure sure I'll push the code
five minutes
continue so people are
like let me know if you want
me to continue please give me thumbs up
if you need a break give me thumbs down
if you allow me to continue we'll
close the class certainly
okay
git add dot
git commit
minus nm
selectors
git push
I'll give you the
link
give me a second
so guys
I forgot the
poll that I asked like whether to continue
thumbs up was for continue
or break
what we are supposed to do when we go for
thumbs down we have to continue is it
I was trying to
commit the code push the code
thumbs down for the break okay
let's get the five minutes
break guys and we'll come back
you please go through the code that
have pushed any doubts you have anything
please let me know okay
and
meanwhile also
check this link you know that link
that I have give you on links dot md
you can go and let's say
I open that here itself
okay
which link I was talking about
go to self study
open this md file
okay you click this one
this will redirect you to
you know web dev web dev is
best for understanding HTML
CSS according to me at least
it gives you clear you know
idea so go through this
explore things also
like you have pseudo classes and
pseudo elements how you can deal with them
so one of the thing that I have already showed you is
nth child like you can how you can deal
with it and hover thing
but there are many other properties
that you have to read and understand
because everything cannot be done it
in projects when we are building I will show
multiple use cases of them
okay
sure
I hope you go and check
all the things that I have shared
okay
please take break guys
you
back
reactions any
reactions guys
so
if you
stay in the call like
We can end the class really like not stretching it that much because the content that I want to discuss now
Or two topics are left. Okay?
Because selectors was big one because I had too many questions to cover
Let me just say like compare, you know recheck it if I have covered everything Oh
Oh
All right, I've covered this one this one done this one done
cool
So any answers guys that went nine questions anyone had thought of it or?
Like anything any combinations that you want to use on this
Oh
This actually this question can be solved if you have understood those first eight questions anyone tried it
Guys did anyone try
Okay, no worries, let's let's move ahead let's move it guys no
So now if we have to discuss something called us
Colors, okay colors in CSS
Say I have an index dot HTML file
HTML5 now, let's say I have something like
A
Diff tag or P tag again lower M
Now if I open the show preview
Now let's say I
Try to add something called as like let's say color or to this one. I'll use a style block here and
I'll use element selector
And let's say I say color to be
Dodger blue, okay. Now I made this color
No ways how many colors you would be able to remember or you will be able to type
Do you think there would be limitation on this
Like seven max to seven or ten right you remember I hardly even remember eight to nine
but if you have any time gone to like, you know any paint shop and
Like if someone has built their home or painted their home, you have to select
color from your catalog, right
Have anyone experienced it like selecting a color from a catalog color code?
You have to you have a color code, right
Does anyone remember that color code how it was represented?
How that color code was represented? I?
Worry like
Some some people are saying hash code and hex right hex. So
Do you alright so what happened right that way like?
Generally in world right if you go for any any places
The colors like this way right whenever you name colors like Dodger blue even I think Dodger blue or something
People might not remember it or know it like can I have a Dodger blue shirt t-shirt this I remember because I was having
That same type of t-shirt. I was searching like how we can get the sky blue or there are different types of blues
So that was one of the Dodger blue
But there is a limitation on this type of color. How many does HTML browser support?
For this we have only 140 colors as a limitation
But if you want to go ahead, right if you want further more colors like same way as we have a different, you know shades of
colors like in like when you see it
Similarly you have if you want to remember multiple like list of things right you go you have like
Defined it in the hex code format now
If you go and see let's say I I say that this is a h3. Let's say I make it this h3
Okay, and let's say I use element selector again. I do h3 and color
No, there's other way as you as you all suggested that we can use a hash code like hash code
Again starts with six letters after that
Okay, there are once you say that hash key there are six things now six things inside this how it goes is like
Let me write down in the comments
This is like hash
red red
green green
blue blue
Okay
So what we say that first like first two letters stands for our
Our is go for it now, let's say if I'd elect and this range right this value of range can grow from
Any number any letter out of this six things can go from range of zero to nine and a to F
Okay, the combination of this. Let's say I define one sort of combination, which is nine a
Nine four
BC
So this is giving us some hash type of color. Okay
So this is giving you this sort of inside the blue
This is giving you some other sort of color and as a developer guys you need not to worry about colors
This is a UX designer headache
But we just should need should need to know that how we can different ways we can use to color a particular element
What are the abilities one is using a direct?
color name
The other way one is using a hex code and the hex code is generally starts with a hash and it goes with RGB
Okay
multiple treat three different things where first RR goes for red Gigi goes for green and blue and
This is how it is made even if I go for any Asian paint shop or anywhere, right? They mix
two to three colors
And generate a new color because they have a fixed formula that how much quantity which one is treated now when I say nine a
It starts from zero to nine and a to F zero being very less and you are F being too much height
Okay. Now if you see
They say that in nine a the adding a less amount of red in it. They're adding
and
And good amount of green in it
But they had more amount of blue in it when you go for B and C because it is going from zero nine a F
So BC is more it means that blue color is more
That's the reason why if you see when I'm over a word it is showing actually inside blue color only you have selected the light
shit
You are able to relate this case like how that color change is happening
Okay
So this is how hex code is used then there is another one. Okay, then there is another one some people might not
That is also not enough for them. So what they have designed is they use some other thing. Let's let's say this is again
h4 tag
Lorem 50
Okay, what they have done no sir. Hey, I don't
It's the same way how this has been represented there is a one extra property you can use it which is called RGB
Okay
Generally, it is defined using RGB itself RGB is a function
We know that we haven't started function, but since you have already completed
We know DSA you might be knowing a basic definition of a function
What it is giving me now when I'm defining RGB RGB goes for again red green blue combination itself
But here you have to define how much percentage you need each value can go up to maximum
240 the range is again
0 to 240, okay
0 to 240
Now let's say if I select 240 as this one
Adding too much of red
Green being completely 0 blue being 0
Okay, and
Alpha this is a opacity. I will come to that. Okay, let's make it one if you see this
Do you see this when I give completely 240 as for the red it is selected last more straight
If I add let's say somewhat of green, let's say I add 100% of green to it
Now if you see this as completed to orange
Because I'm adding green to it. Now, let's say if I add blue to it
Let's say I add much of blue to it
Now if you see the color is changing and the fourth parameter
Which is one what I mean is like opacity how much you want to see clearly if I give it zero
You cannot see it anything if I give 0.5. This is like light shaded
0.6 or 0.7
We can use RGB RGB color like hex code and RGB and simple color
There are three different types of defining it and this is one one among this now
if
Any doubts guys any doubts till now in the whole class that we have discussed
Because I will show one more thing which is called has a HSL
This is actually rarely used actually I
I
Never have written myself
Okay, but I'll show it like how does it work if you see it here
This is like a when you say a photographer who edits right photos like once you have done it they add
hue saturation and lightness
so
Considered this one this both saturation and lightness are working by percentage systems which goes from 0 to 100
Hue is something which is going from 0 to 360 in circle. Okay, when I say hue you goes for different colors
Okay, you were something like you can say that the different colors in a circle whenever you are rotating rotating like a clock, right?
We are pointing to different thing color will keep changing
Like if I show you if I do this one, right if you see orange yellow
Green and everything is changing colors will be keep changing. Okay, that's how hue works
Coming back at the last if you come back at after 360 degrees again to the zero it will be ready itself
You but when it comes to lightness if you give complete lightness
100% you won't be able to see anything
It would be white even if you if you give zero it will become completely darkness like without any light in the night
How you can say complete dark lightness stands for that thing?
Okay, and is this clear guys how light lightness and hue works?
Because I'll apply it but this is you know, better interface to show it
Okay. Similarly, there's something called saturation. Now, let's say if I go for saturation what is happening if you see here
This is you know adding a shade to that particular color. You have selected red color
You have given the lightness but how much light is shade you want to add like
Different shades of that particular color only the that is used for a saturation you wanted a saturation same thing
You go for your anything editing your profile any picture right in your mobiles also
You will able to see these three options like lightness which is brightness and saturation and hue the same thing
Okay, this is something we get rarely utilized when we are coding it
But this is a one of the way that you can use to color the no elements. Okay. I'll show you one of the thing
Let's say
Again, I'll use a hedge fight ag
It's a lorem5
And let's say h5
Going with the color then let's say HSL I
Give you as a let's say 0 to
360 so let's say I give 2 3 3 then saturation is in terms of percentage. Let's say 23%
Then let's say lightness could be
34%
You see I've added something like a black in color. Let's say we make this one as a
45% if you see this had become a blue, let's say if we change this 335 it will be still that 70
It will change the color
Okay, I hope you got the basic idea of like what are the different types of you know
We have colors like I'm in different types of ways of adding a color to an
HTML element
Right. So let's summarize this one guys on the iPad
Okay when it comes to colors right
Coloring any HTML element you have four things specifically one is directly color
But it has a limitation since the colors can exist only from a max of 140
Okay, when it comes to hex codes
You have a hex code of defining it. This is mostly used
At least my workplace of the experience that I have mostly I've used hex codes
Mostly I've used hex codes to code to add colors to an any
You know attribute any HTML elements or content, okay?
Xcode generally after hash you have six letters, which is rrbbgg
Okay, and this range is going from 0 to 9 and then a to f 0 being less
F being highest
Okay, then you had something called RGB
Function where you can directly define the collect the percentage of RGB now this goes from 0 to
240 you can give our
Range from 0 to 240 it need to you need to pass three
parameters to it
Sorry arguments to it
0 to 240
Similarly you has also HSL is stand for you you is having 0 to
360 degrees which can you can use color then saturation and
Let's say
And
Lightness
Both are having 0 to 100% of in terms of percentage
Okay RGB is still 255
Give me a second
RGB is still 255 is it
Oh
Just a second 255
Let me confirm this guys
Yeah, sorry 255 pardon me guys. Thank you for correcting me
The rich it goes for 255 inch
Okay 0 to 255 inch
Okay
So guys, I hope this is this might not be much interesting one
But this is how you add multiple types of colors. I hope this is clear. There's nothing much
Interesting in it, isn't it?
No reactions guys, I hope this is clear guys any doubts in this
Okay, so I have one quiz for you
Okay, let's say I'll play the quiz
Okay, I didn't share my okay fine I've corrected this 255 I'll launch the quiz guys
Yeah, yeah sure
Can anyone see this see the quiz
I
See eight users have participated at least like 70% of them should answer it
Come on like I
See
Fifty more than 50% of them have answered
So I'll end the quiz guys now if you see the people who have
Voted 67% or 140. That's right
I've just written on the iPad and I have also on the screen this one right if you go and see I've told
Right. There are only 140 like things that you can write it down
There's a limitation on the class
That's a reason why we went to X code then RGB X code and RGB both are saying same thing where you are adding a green
red green and blue combination and
making
So this is also our return and reverse
GP
Okay
So that's how colors are working now
till now let's let's
Let's move to the next topic as like so on this itself. I want to add one more thing is that
Have you seen newspapers with like unique fonts like anytime like unique unique fonts
Like if you see some newspapers are having different styling, right?
Calligraphy sort of things and some are having different things
right
How can you deal with that? Let's say now
Here we are having color. Now this this is some type of content
That is there which is like first lorem, which is in the paragraph time
Now let's say if you want to have different types of it, right?
Let's say I had go if you want to apply different types of font style font cells
You have to go for font family first. Then you have to select it. Okay, you have many things which are existing
Okay, let's say I go and select Times New Roman because this is something everyone have seen it or
Like whenever you go for Microsoft Word, many people have might have used Times New Roman, right?
a font family
Or else let's say you go and apply different types of it. Let's say what all available
Let's say Helvetica now if you see this this thing has got changed now, but
There are also limitations on this there are also limitations on this like but now how can you
Get it like now if you see this there are also limitations on this
But how can you add it like for colors? We had this limitation. We got something new
And something new and something new extra options that you can manage with but for fonts, right what happened is like, you know this
Google has given us one site where
Like if you go for Google font family site, right they gave you all the list of you know
different types of fonts that you can select because if you say this is something like a
Different Mongolian language, right if you go and see this one
If you want to write in Mongolian, you can use this like how how would you use this?
I'll show it like but there are too many different
You know types of fonts that you can write down and you can use it in your
projects, okay
Now let's say if you select one thing
This is something you have seen in the cartoons maybe because that's where that's how you know, the headings used to come in childhood
Like everyone has a right to fit this particular thing
But if you see the newspaper one that I was talking about I'm scrolling through trying to find that one a
Bit of a calligraphy type of font
Not able to found
But let's do one thing. Let's use something. Okay, let's use this one. Okay
So now whenever you want to use a particular font, right you can go to the particular who are providing us
One way of is getting is like this one Google fonts
Now let's say I what you can do is like you can click on the plus here on the right side and
Here you will have a link link shades
Like if you see I can what I'll do is like I'll copy this link shades. Let's say I go and
copy in our code base
Now all the links should be added in meta because body doesn't need to have anything
Now one of the link that we earlier added is like, you know
Relation was style sheet now something we are added is like in href. We gave Google fonts link
And we also given the other Google API's. We are importing them like what we are importing
We are hitting their URL with family as a tech tool
Okay, and we defined style sheet
Relation as style sheet now once we have done this now what we can do is like we can go back and use this particular
Style that we have done. How would you do that?
It's also defined here itself, like let's say I copy this font family and
I
Go and let's say I update this particular thing second thing which is history
Now if you see that particular type of font is applied
Okay. So if you want to build any unique websites, right which are having different fonts and different things of you know, reading
Ability you can always use Google fonts and download those fonts and use it. Okay, wherever you want to use
Let's say let's play around with something else. Also, let's let's do
some
Let's try to add this Chinese one whether this would work
Okay, let's remove this. Let's go down and add this
Click on the plus
Okay, why am I able to not access this
Give me a second guys
I'm getting this now
Let's say I again copy this all the slings
We can remove few of the things that we don't need again, which are duplicating it. Let's say I see this
We need this link
We need won't we don't need this font Google API's because this is something we have already used it
removing this one and
Preconnect also I don't need I just need extra link which is trying to download this particular font
No, what I'll do is like I'll go and copy this particular
Okay font family, let's say this family
And I'll add it to this particular h4
Okay, now if you see this what happened guys
Okay, if you see the font here it's something like different you see here notice hands are like showing different thing
But if you convert into two and again into English, this is how it will look like but here what we applied is like this
comma sanctuary like how this is like
Working is like you should understand is that if there is something like content is written this way
Let's say I copy that content. Also. I copy this content
Let's say I copy this content it would reflect still that in the same way
If you see
It makes that font much readable and much better and way to understand and view like all these fonts
Okay, that's how Mongolian have they added specific to Mongolian because
Mongolian, maybe they need that right amount of spaces and way to understand better
Okay, so you have to use the respective font families and different type of things that you have
But you know one thing that I want to say is that all this work, right?
Which one to select which type of color to select is not a
Friend and developer job or a full stack developers job. This is something
designers do
Designers are the people who try to
Select the color and give it to you. You are just a person like hey where I have to use how to use they already
Tell told us that we are the developers will you just develop that thing?
Okay, but I'm just showing it like if you're building something anything personal project how you can access the different types of fonts. Okay
So
Any doubts guys with respect to how we can access the fonts or how we can do it
I'll add this link also Google links
Fonts, let's say I'm not pinning in the chat because I'm adding all here. Okay
What if the font is installed in that doesn't work that way
Open the it like because you are rendering it on a browser, right? If browser supports you can deal with it
Yeah, it's it's how that HTML parsing is happening if it is supported by that browser browser will be able to understand it
Because these are the API is that you're downloading that particular font at the runtime
These are converting the type of format that should be rendered
Okay
Because this HTML is entered in browser you have to all think thing in terms of perspective of browser
Can we upload somewhere
Use yeah, this is how they have done it right? They uploaded on the cloud and you are using it
Using a link tank. That's it
But you cannot do it on a browser because you are not some more person like
They don't have they have not made that open right that someone can upload it and can be reused it
So is that you don't define it and you automatically get it
Okay
Cool so guess we covered
Colors now one thing that left is we have to cover background properties
I'll just go to the background properties and then I'll go to the background properties
Left is we have to cover background properties
I'll show you one of the things like one of the topic that how you can deal with a background property
Of CSS, let's say I create a background. I create a HTML file
index.html
so let's say
HTML5 and
Background
Properties
So this is one of the unique property that for people to face challenge to understand this
Reason I'll tell you let's say I copy some content for you
Our diff tag
Say I have this and I render this
No
Let's say
No, so have any anyone observed right there are many use cases where you see that there's a image behind the scene a content
on top of it like
There is an image like behind the scene
You see that there is something like a river image and there's some messages coming over it
Like on the channels or the on the pictures whenever you print some greetings or stuff, right?
So that is where the background comes in like let's see how you can add those images and how can you deal with that?
Okay, what I am doing it here is that I'm adding a style block
Again, let's say style inside this since I have a class background attached. I'll use a dot class
I'm a class
Element, I mean class attribute, you know ways of select selector
now
one property
To have a background image or anything is that you have to select background image
Property itself, but here you cannot give an image PNG or anything always this files are in terms of like bigger in size
So you are always supposed to give a URL to it. Okay
Now inside this URL function you are supposed to pass a particular website
Or the location of particular that you are where it is. Well, where can I get that you are now?
Let's say I go into any particular side
River images
Let's say I have this I go and select this let's say copy image address
If you see this now, there's a unique interesting problem guys now, do you see what's happening here?
Can anyone tell me what's actually happening here
Repeat is happening image repeat is happening, right? So this this behavior, right only this behavior people
Fail to handle it. Now, let's say I give some background
Size also
Okay, like like let's say we define a size. Let's say we say that 400 pixel
Now if you see the picture is getting disoriented if I give 400, let's say if I give 450 also
Okay, or let's say 500
If I give 550 it won't repeat it will get it will come only one time
But you see this picture is getting disoriented now for those reuse cases, right?
You what you have to deal how you can do it, right? You have one of the property called like background repeat
So you can say one thing is that
Like you can say that if you want to repeat or you would want to repeat you how you want to deal it
Like let's say no repeat. It will say that whatever size of picture is there now by default it will take that
But there are some pictures
Where you want to only repeat it on x-axis like let's say on the horizontal way
Like when I say x-axis like only one thing you don't want to repeat multiple times
Let's say so you can say that repeat x and you do it
It will come for only one row if you want to do it for y you can do it for only one way
But if you give repeat it will repeat it all the time
Is this property clear guys how you can do handle this repeat property?
Okay
So if you if you are having an image and your background image and that background image is not supporting if that size is
Small and you know content is way too high
Then you can use one three things one is once you give URL you can use background repeat
Then you can play around with let's say
background size
And you say you say 200 pixel
Now let's say you say that
Repeat X
Okay, but I have one of the image that I had it
So like if you do know one
unsplash.com
This is actually a site which gives you actually really beautiful images
Like if you want to use any time right you can go and get it rather than directly going to Chrome
I'll also do one thing like I'll have it here
Like if you want to build your personal project, and then you want to use
Fetch the images, let's say
How do I write clean images?
Then
Then let's say if I write beautiful images I feel like bit yeah free images
Okay, let's say we go to this
Site let's say we copy this now you can always like go
And copy image address so no one will you know copyright issues you
Know if you see
Still that image seems to be short for us like if I because I've given a background size to it
Let's say remove this
Now the picture is way too big for this one content, okay?
Let's say I gave this I say this as a 400 pixel
So I make 300
Okay, anyways, I have one image readily so I'll copy that and I'll show it to you
But where did I get that images like again unsplash let me minimize this
Delete this particular thing I'll copy it. So what did I selected one random person who was actually a fishing it and
Let's say I make a no repeat
This should come actually in write-in size, but it's not coming up let's say I can give another property, which is
background
Position so it will help us to
Yeah, it is help us to move that to different positions one of what I'm using is like I'm using Center and
So one of the suggestions that I got from Teja was to
So one of the suggestions that I got from Teja was that to use background size cover
Let's say if I use cover
Okay, yeah that works too Teja
So I comment this
But it's not coming in Center
It will cover the whole content as you said that it will cover the whole content whatever it is needed
But if you want to pull that again image into Center, you have to use this and let's say I say background
Repeat to no repeat
Okay, so this is how you can play with a different background, you know
Properties that you have many people face challenge in putting it in right way. Like how you can you deal with it?
So this is how you can use it on multiple places
So there's any doubts on this
Till now any any doubts like if you have any doubts, please
Let me know
Because this is what the content that I want to cover today
The content part is over for today
Like one thing we can do is like if you want me to build HTML right for the
That portfolio project I can build that but today's content related to whatever CSS. I want to get started with it is covered
Transform scale in images that that thing is bit advanced will show it like in project specific itself some bit
Okay
But yeah, there are too many things to explore on CSS terms
Right. There are too many things to explore since today is an interaction class itself
So I will show you how to do that
There are too many things to explore since today is an interaction class itself where we have introduced a different
types of
Firstly, what is CSS then?
Different ways of adding a CSS like maybe in a file writing in style block or internal external once you have cleared on that
Different ways of selecting a tag then applying CSS styles to it
I've seen colors like different types then background images font styles. We have covered good part of content it content
Then tomorrow will have more on like on the next class next week
The classes are going to be much interesting because we'll see
Responsive layouts box model right flex boxes grid so that that that would be really interesting things will be having it in next week
Okay, so nice can I start out session
Will come we'll cover that some within next week, okay, I see one thumbs down
Okay, let's let's start with a doubt session guys
If you have any doubts, please stay in class
If you don't have doubts, you can feel free to drop off and enjoy your weekend. Please do assignments guys
Let me know if you have any challenge
I know I've seen few comments about you know compiler not being working rightly like the test cases are not working rightly
Right. So I have flagged it to the team because that's developers team who have to handle it scalar
That they have to write a right unit test cases, right?
Like when they are cheap when they're doing it and the processing speed is also slow. So the work is on
So your feedback works really in a positive way for us
So we'll we'll start to improve it because even if you see right if you go
Anywhere like you want to go and solve any like problems based on?
HTML or CSS there are no websites build assets now like if you go for problem-solving
You go for
Elite code you go for
Like, you know geek for cakes you go for a scalar you go for an interview bit
There are multiple people who have already built those in sons in
Like engines and passing that code now if you want to write some unit test cases, which is passing
Understanding HTML and writing it down
People are trying to solve that bigger problem as of now because once scalar does it properly
Maybe they'll be built it like an interview bit for the friends folks
Because now that domain on the front-end right is having a different scope
Now people are coming up learning front-end in like, you know in depth and that
Domain is being built as strong as the back-end and even the full stackers. So this is going there's a huge scope down the lane
right
So even someone can build an engine which can
Understand and pass this like, you know this problem-solving unit test cases
That's really cool problem to solve even if you think from a problem-solving perspective as of now
What's running behind the scene is node.js server?
Which is running the unit test cases like checking
Generating a dom like if someone who understands the dom
Once your HTML is submitted
Whatever you have to write written down that goes on to the server now that that once they receive that
they have written some list of unit test cases, which
Generates a dom of your copy and then the check the particular thing is there or not there
So that's where you know, and even as somebody pointed out standardization code for HTML
Oh
Standardization, you know, there are multiple formats like you know, the one is a older HTML
Now is there's a there's a HTML 5, right?
so if you see right, let's whenever I write down even the HTML right, let's say if I
Create a index.html file. I
Say HTML you see I'm getting three types of image itself if I use HTML Excel
So this is something, you know
W3 or 1999 is the old format right if I write simple HTML
This is like third version then there is something called HTML 5
Where when I generate this by default, I'm getting one of the meta tag, which is saying this
X UA compatible content IE edge what this is saying is that well if you remember we hired one of the
You know daily browser Internet Explorer
Which was bit old because Microsoft never paid attention to it
They started a different project called Microsoft edge, right and they didn't add new releases on that
now when someone like banks, right the
Whatever banks has been in the Europe or the most of the banks what they used to prefer is they used to prefer
Internet Explorer because that was used to come with a default software
Default of Microsoft software because Windows was a powerful OS that was installed in every desktop and desktop was a
Mode of using a computer in 1990s till 2005 7 till that laptops
Error came in. Okay. So Internet Explorer was a major
Important browser other than this Netscape or Mozilla Firefox Chrome was a different generation level
Okay, so this meta tax what they're saying is that hey Internet Explorer
Please use newest HTTP equivalent compatible rendering engine to pass this HTML code
so we are specifically saying that you know browser to use this this is not needed anymore because
Microsoft itself has removed support for Internet Explorer and that is that project is being shut down
Right. There is no support for that. I mean there is no engineer
Will help you out even if you face any challenge or struck on that, right? So
Similarly, if you see this utf character 8 also utf 8. So if you know like we have
Does anyone know this word ask I?
I mean you have done already
DSSO you should be knowing right ask a ask a someone like which is having a to Z
Then capital a to capital Z
Then you have zero to nine, right all this support which comes under asking like
encoding, but this is not enough to render a Chinese language or they'll go for or
Tamil type Malayali type right fonts. So this I mean this type of messages are not able to end
So under utf 8, right?
This has a very large encoding pattern this was developed after the ask I which can ask I is only supported for
English format, but if you go for other languages, you need this utf 8 encoding to convert those HTML now imagine
That we have copied one code, right of a different Mongolian language format
If you don't have this utf 8 character some browser engines might not be able to parse it
Still chrome might be a smart enough to handle it by itself
But there are some older browsers which don't have support. They need some extra additional
Information that they have to use this right?
So there are some smart people there are not some so smart people. So yeah, Unicode encoding, right?
So and yeah, this is for responsiveness this I'll explain like what is exactly happening here once we start with
responsive websites
Okay, this is pretty simple, but straightforward. I'll explain
So standardization of HTML comes with browser support guys if you have let's say there is no
Who is pioneering browser? What do you think?
Who is pioneering browser like which browser do Firefox?
Chrome
Go do you know on this thing? Do you know this thing?
Google right since this is a doubt session. I'll talk for some time
Let's say how much Google pays
To keep chrome as default
So the pioneer right the pioneer
The pioneer is chrome. I'll tell you I mean Firefox team is the Netscape team, right? Firefox is someone who has written
DnDocs
MDN is like people right whoever has been
If you go and ask him anyone right they'll suggest like hey if you want to learn web development go to MDN docs, okay
That's our best thing that you can refer to. Okay, they have been you know updating it since 2005
Which is like almost 18 years. Okay, you can go to understand web API CSS nesting HTML and everything they have
too much depth of
content but for me, right
Like I want something new way to understand read things I found web dev right web dev is really
To the next level. This is again built by this content is actually handled by Google itself
You can explore this one, right?
They have too many things like talking about PWI have score web vitals performance explaining CSS UI designs
Right there too many things need good things are happening around it. You can go and explore learn
What are the links that I've been providing you are from here because they're also what like let's say if I go for HTML
Right if I open go and let's say
Tables
Right you go to a read article some of them also have a you know podcast recorded for that
I'll show you one of the podcast. I
Mean while I was learning it we didn't have this beautiful
website built, okay
I
Learn go back to
CSS I was actually searching for better sites that I can add it
in that
Links, so I went to selectors because I wanted to give now if you see this, there's a podcast
So you can even listen the podcast when you are traveling anywhere. You don't want to see it
Just put a earphone understand the podcast. So your web development is just like going through that. It will be stored in mind like
You go and select us. You'll remember like this
Okay, you don't have no one will come and able will be able to fool you out or you will face any challenge with that
Okay, so go through them. It would be really piece of cake
So
Yeah, now I was talking about Google right they they are actually pioneers in that
They're paying many companies like billions of dollars like somebody has registered
18 billion rupees they paid it to
App to make room as a default engine like in your mobile in your mobile
You hardly go on a different browser other than crew. Do you agree?
You hardly at least for laptop basis you install
Firefox you install if you are on Mac
You might be installing Safari and deleting it right using it
But when it comes to like Android mobiles, of course, they they own it
They have their own OS Android on OS is there's their own India tried to build one OS
I think Bharat OS that didn't click it. We don't have manufacturers in in India
Can support it Bharat OS if you know anyone if anyone knows knows that but Android stack is their own
They keep on developing new and it's stuck. So whoever install that software by default engine is
In mobiles that particular thing is crew. Okay chrome search engine
But if you go for other OS's right which had like, you know some
Chinese companies has their own OS 1 plus has their own OS
Apple has their own OS
But whatever mobile ecosystem so this company Google goes and pay them that hey, please make our
browser as a default
What they're getting in back if you use more you search more they're getting that amount of data
Now data is being king. If you know the data you can write
Models on that like any LED models
Last more you then you can do you can understand people's perspective and you can do many things
So that's why they are paying it
You should be knowing it actually does anyone know the table changes that happened recently
with
open AI company
Everyone knows it right Instagram in Instagram them in many memes on it
Their CEO
Being removed from as a CEO then being bought into Microsoft again resigning from Microsoft going back to that place
Microsoft has also need to release new one chatbot
Copilot I guess
You should explore this this is actually supposed to you know
The is a chat GPT
That will be specific to Windows right Windows OS
I guess you don't need because Windows again whoever own OS right operating system
They have much of abilities to deal with it
So you can explore this that's also one of the unique thing I mean learn one thing be great one skill set
But keep an open eye
So guys I kept on talking for some time, but if you have any doubts, please let me know
Happy to you know take them understand it right if you want to build something unique right unique things
So you want to build something new thing?
if you're facing any challenge share with that get up link and
Write it down in the chat
I can help you out or the others can help you out if you want me to work out work on that
Tack me that tack me the cloud AI completely take our front-end engineers
No, no somebody. It's never going to happen. It's never going to happen. No one can automize automate everything
Can we build like an online editor as a project? You can build anything project are like
I'm
Asking you like if you let's say if you build if you ask right you go and say like if it is some imagine
There's some latency when you are I've gave you already a problem statement you can think of it
like this if you go for lead code if you go for
If you go for lead code or gig for kicks
There's able to parse your code of different languages and they're able to execute it and get your
N-number of test cases like the thousand or two thousand test cases executed and within seconds and they're getting a response back
That's not happening for HTML part
Like if you think that as a problem statement just think of it like what should be done behind the scene
Like how can you write a test cases for that one?
Because if you are able to solve this problem
You might you are getting hired
In inside this team itself like if you come with a problem statement you ping on shuman. Hey, this is happening
I found a problem and this is a solution to it
It would be cool isn't it so you have to just I
Mean if you if you have a major sites, right major sites working in open domain
You being internally you knowing it if you are adding something to their product, right?
You are having really good pitch to them at least like it's like a strong referral
That you are directly you're showcasing by the action
Right, so
Do it that way do something unique try to go like there are many people who try to find problems in the actual sites and reporting them
and
Even right if you see a problem
you
Like there are many websites, right if you go into the github.com
Get up calm simply get up calm. Don't go anywhere like it up calm just find
React
Okay, go for Facebook react, okay
This is a actual react code base, right react code base like whole react project
Whatever project was developed by Facebook itself
now
If I go here and go into the issues, there are too many problems with this framework yet. You see
These many problems are there
There is a bug there are many things that are happening. Why don't you pick one and solve it? This is what opens forces, right?
Like and imagine what this thing is written on
If you go behind the scene what this thing is written on just go and see like, okay react
They have written what are the languages are being used behind us and if you see
same HTML CSS C++
JavaScript typescript coffee script. Okay
See too many things are there JavaScript being
How people found bug in Google Insta website as much as you use it somewhere as you found as your people found bugs in
Scalar editor like whenever typing HTML same way
You have to keep using it to find out and if there is a pattern repeating it same thing. So it's a bug
Okay, you can report the bug or you can suggest three things
Okay, you can report the bug or you can suggest it like typing down email and sending it to big people
Or if you know right there are many people what they do really this this is like they attack people at the LinkedIn itself
Like if this is a bug
And tagging directly if you see this happens with a zero that mostly
because
Yeah, they earn money from it, but it depends on the type of post you are writing it
Because this happened with zero the recently because there is a huge trading volume was happening and their servers were not working as expected
so
What happened then is like people lost their bets too many
so people have tagged them that hey we lost because of this thing this issues because
That on zero that it's something that is happening is real money, right trading things. So imagine
the effect that you have
so
That's how you report a problem or you build your own like solution to it
so both ways works now
Imagine in get out and react project right this person is someone who had large amount of commit and high amount of code return
You see in between he didn't have any contributions added, but he kept doing recently also
Now if you go and search him in the LinkedIn, right you will be able to find his working at
This kind of team itself actual team
He gave his email ID and Twitter. Let's say go for his Twitter handle and x.com
Okay, so let's say is her Dan Abramov. Let's go to LinkedIn and search his name
Where is working and what this is how you reach out people at least I do personally
Because you need any mentor that you have to work with in future or anything. Let's say go into LinkedIn comms
And then what's his spelling
This is not the person
Let's say this is himself
Go below he's working with NASA SpaceX
No, you may not be the person
Who has built this
Maybe we are searching a wrong person, but
I have to see like who people are, you know, handling this reporting this or building your actual frameworks that you are using it
Cool guys
If you don't have any doubts, then let me know we can end the session for today
And we meet back on Tuesday and come back and learn more on it
Hope you are having good time guys
Hope you are able to catch up and able to understand the topics that I am discussing
Because down the road, I am going to be talking about some of the topics that I am going to be talking about
Because down the line, right? We'll take it up a bit with face where you will be able to you know
If you keep revising, it would be a piece of cake. You won't even know when the full stack was completed
Okay
Just stay still. I'll be there with you to handle things
Okay, just keep doing assignments. Keep revising the notes that I'm saying, you know get up repo
Keep exploring if you don't understand while exploring or reading any content reach me out. I'll try to help you out. Okay
cool guys then
Thank you guys for attending to this session. See you in the next class
Thank you muneshwara
Our assignments enough never
assignments
Are basic that are needed but when it comes to project development, that's that's been that's been uh, you know thing
So somebody has question like our assignments enough to good enough to you know
Able to build projects because uh, mostly that one stack or the java stack or anything that you pick it up front end back end anything
Until unless you build projects, right?
The actual projects where you put the hyperlinks
Till then nothing is enough
Okay
You have to build projects. You have to see how you can build it currently since
We are only on html and css part. You might not be able to build complete projects using that powerful projects
Once we cover things slowly, right once your javascript is covered once your react is covered
So i'll i'll ask you to build projects on react more because that's that's what you are going to put links on
Your resume because i'll help you build few projects three to four projects that you can add directly
On uh, you know get your resume like one of the full stack project that we'll build is
Uh, you know book my show a full stack project where you learn authentication authorization database all things end to end
Which you can link it directly in your resume deploying it on your uh, you know cloud
second thing
I'll also help you build one imdb project which will be completely based on react and redux that you can link it
Okay, the portfolio project that i'll share the code base with you is not good enough
But you can uh, you can you can replicate that one that will be helpful for our practicing html and css
But you have to build projects something that's that's a single statement that I can say
You have to build projects and those projects should be added in your resume
Is that clear like
Okay, yeah
Great guys
then I think i'll keep on speaking guys, uh, so
Thank you for attending today's session. I'll uh, see you on the tuesday class where we learn box model one of the core important concepts
of css
Okay
Yeah, yeah, let's build online id. There's a many projects are going on to on id also
Competing microsoft and google are competing because both people are software companies
Google's id is something new thing. That's idx project ids. I guess you can search on that you can read more on that
Okay, so look I said good night
You